hello everyone and welcome to another
blender made easy tutorial today i'll be
showing you how to create this book
opening animation in blender this is
actually pretty easy to create and we're
going to be covering a variety of topics
including constraints animation and a
couple other things so let's go ahead
and get started
the first thing i'm going to do of
course is delete the default cube so
make sure it's selected and delete it
then what you can do is shift a and add
in a new cube we're going to be modeling
a very basic book right here it's not
going to be a very complex it's just
going to be three different cubes so
with this first cube selected i'm going
to press n and go over to the dimensions
tab
the dimensions of this cube is going to
be 0.2 for the x and
.05 for the z
this is going to be a pretty thin cube
and this is going to be the spine of the
book
next up i'm going to go into top view
and shift d it this is going to be the
right cover so i'm going to name this
cover and then right and we'll select
the other cube and we'll just call this
spine
with the cover right the x dimension is
going to be a little bit bigger we're
going to go with 1.5 for the x then
let's move it into place so press g and
x holding control and shift you can
place it right next to it just like that
let's shift d this and place it on the
other side and we're going to call this
one cover and then left
now that we have all of our objects in
our scene let's work on the rotation of
the book so it can actually open and
close
to do this it's actually going to be
pretty easy we're going to select the
spine of the book and we're going to
create two different pivot points for
the spine to do this go into edit mode
and go into the edge select mode and
select this top edge right here i'm
going to press shift s and go cursor to
select it
next i'm going to press shift a and add
in a new empty object and it's just
going to be a single arrow let's add
that in and scale it down i'm also going
to press ctrl a and apply the scale so
everything works correctly and then
let's duplicate that and place it on the
other side so press shift d and then x
type in point 2 in the negative
direction and enter to actually get the
spine of the book to rotate around these
two points we're going to select it and
then add a new constraint
the constraint that we're going to be
adding is a pivot constraint this allows
us to select a new pivot point for the
object even though the origin is in the
center this will act like a new origin
point so for the target it's going to be
the empty on the right you also want to
make sure that the rotation range is set
to the positive y direction so make sure
it's positive y and select it
we'll add in a new pivot point and it's
going to be for the empty on the left
side so for the target it's going to be
the empty on the left and the rotation
range this time is going to be negative
y so now what happens is if we select
our object and press r and y you can see
it's rotating along that point just like
that
now before we continue creating the book
animation here is a quick word from our
sponsor once again this video is brought
to you by skillshare skillshare is an
online learning platform with thousands
of classes taught by professionals they
have a huge variety of subjects and
topics that you'll never run out of
things to learn some of the topics
include animation illustration graphic
design music and they even have a lot of
blender classes one class i can
recommend is character illustration by
gabriel piccolo he goes into depth on
the process of creating a character
drawing it out on a piece of paper and
it's actually really good if you're
wanting to get into character design and
learning how to draw faces and
illustration and things like that this
class is perfect with the premium
membership you get unlimited access to
every single class on their platform
this also means that there's going to be
no ads and you can study without any
interruption i've been using skillshare
for a really long time and i can
definitely recommend it
so here's the deal the first 1000 people
to click the link in the description or
the pin comment will get one month of
the premium membership for free so what
are you waiting for click the link down
below and start learning something new
today thanks again to skillshare for
sponsoring this video now let's get back
to the tutorial
next up we're going to work on the two
covers on each side this is also going
to be pretty easy what we're going to
first do is select the cover on the
right and we want to make sure the
origin is right at that empty point so
with it selected i'm going to right
click set origin and then the origin to
the 3d cursor
let's do the same thing on the other
side select this empty press shift s and
go cursor to select it then of course
just set it right here origin to 3d
cursor
how this works is we're going to add in
another constraint and it's going to be
a copy rotation constraint
we're going to change the mix to the add
function and this will add rotation so
when this object moves around it's going
to rotate this object as well i also
want to parent both of the covers to the
spine so select the spine at last hit
ctrl p and then parent it to the spine
so now what happens is if we select it
and then rotate it you can see they're
rotating both the covers
going back over to the left cover the
target for this constraint is going to
be the spine so select it and then i'm
also going to limit the rotation of this
i don't want it to actually go
underneath the ground so we're going to
make sure it stops rotating right at
this point
so to do that with the limit rotation
we're going to select the y and the max
value is going to be set up to 180
degrees
also make sure you turn on effect
transform
let's do that exact same process on the
other cover as well so select it
click add constraint and copy rotation
the target is going to be the spine and
then for the
mix mode we're going to select add
then of course the last constraint is
going to be the limit rotation because i
don't want it to go underneath the
ground so select the limit rotation
y and this time for the minimum value
we're going to go with a value of
negative 180 degrees
also make sure you turn on effect
transform
now what happens is if we select our
spine and rotate this along the y you
can see the book will close and then if
we go on the other side the book will
close on that side as well
now before we add in the pages let's do
a little bit of animating on this book
cover first off i'm going to rotate this
along the y till 90 degrees and you
don't want to go past 92 degrees because
you'll see this is what happens make
sure whenever you're rotating it that
you stop exactly at 90 degrees
on frame 1 i'm going to hit i and add in
a rotation keyframe to the spine next
we're going to go to frame a 15 and then
press alt r to reset the animation i'm
going to hit i and add in another
rotation keyframe
then we're going to skip to frame 30 and
rotate this along the y in the negative
direction
all the way to negative 90 then hit i
and add in another rotation keyframe
make sure you hold ctrl when you do this
so it can actually snap to the 5 degree
increments as you can see here don't
worry about the speed of the animation
we're going to be changing these
keyframes later these are just
placeholders
next up we are ready to start adding in
the paper i'm going to create a new
collection on the right side and we're
going to call this pages
then i'm going to go into top view and
then add in the piece of paper so i'm
going to press shift a and add in a new
mesh and it's going to be a plane
let's go into wireframe so we can see
what we're doing and then let's go into
edit mode we need to make sure the
origin is right on the edge of this
plane so i'm going to press g and then x
and drag it over so it's right on the
edge
go out of edit mode and then holding
control i'm going to place it right next
to the edge then you can also scale it
down along the x and the y so it's
actually inside the book alright so we
have the size of the page correct now we
need to subdivide this and add a couple
different modifiers
so what i'll do is i'll go into edit
mode hit control r and we're going to
add 40 loop cuts so press 40 enter and
then right click to make sure they're
centered just like that
next up the modifier that we're going to
be adding is a simple deform modifier
this will have the paper actually bend
as it's moving up
so go over to the modifier tab click add
modifier and then select the simple
deform modifier
for the type it's going to be set to the
bend mode and then for the access it's
going to be the z-axis
currently though this does not look that
good and you can see it's rotated along
the wrong direction so what we need to
do is actually go into side view by
pressing three and then go into edit
mode
select everything with a and then rotate
it by 90 degrees holding ctrl i'm going
to snap it to this axis just like that
go out of edit mode and then rotate it
back
there you can see it's actually rotating
in the correct direction this time now
we can animate the angle right here
i'm going to be setting this down to
zero on frame one and then add in a
keyframe next we're going to skip to
frame 15 and then we're going to set
this to a negative value you can imagine
the page actually flying outwards and
it's going to bend in this direction
yeah this direction the negative value
so set this down to negative
then add in another keyframe
skip to 15 frames later on frame 30 and
we're gonna set this back down to zero
enter and then add in finally that last
keyframe and there we go we now have the
animation of this working now let's add
in the last modifier and then we can
start duplicating the pages
there is one problem with our animation
and the problem is that the beginning of
the page right here is not staying
connected to the spine of the book
this does not really look good and it
totally breaks the animation so how
we're going to fix this is by adding a
hook modifier to make sure it stays
right at the spine of the book
to do this i'm going to go into top view
and press shift s and then click on
cursor to select it
then let's add in a new object i'm going
to press shift a and add in an empty
object we'll just go with a plain axis
and scale it down
this is the object that we're gonna have
the page being hooked to
i'm gonna press ctrl a and apply the
scale make sure you do that that's very
important then let's grab both the paper
and that empty that we just added and
drag it up because currently it's right
inside and that's not very good so let's
drag it up just slightly just like that
all right so what we need to do is
select the page and then add in a new
modifier let's go with the hook modifier
right here what the hook modifier does
is it allows you to take an object and
have another object hooked to it and you
can manipulate it and it will stay in
that exact position
and of course the object that we're
going to be hooking to is that empty
that we just added so click on the
eyedropper tool and select the empty
right there
the other thing that we want to do is
add in a vertex group because right at
this point right here i want the page to
actually be up like this but i also want
it to be laying down on its side over
here
so we're going to be adding in a
gradient weight effect so that only some
parts of the mesh is actually hooked to
the spine to do this we're going to go
into the weight paint mode up top here
and then go into top view
let's restart the animation so it's
laying flat and then select the gradient
tool in top left if we then click and
drag holding control so it locks it to
the x-axis we're going to drag it out
just slightly probably around there or
so looks pretty good only a little bit
with that done we can go out of weight
paint back into object mode and then
select the vertex group that we just
created
now what happens is if we play our
animation
and oh we i forgot to do one more thing
we need to actually parent the empty to
the spine of the book so select the
empty and then select the spine
last hit control p and then parent it to
the object
now if we play our animation you can see
the paper is actually staying stuck to
the spine and that's exactly what we
want
i'm also going to select the paper right
click and shade it smooth alright so now
that we've added the hook and the simple
deform we are ready to start duplicating
the page
i'm going to zoom in and select both the
empty and the piece of paper and then
press shift d and drag it up along the z
axis just slightly
the closer you have the pages together
the more that will be added i'm probably
going to go with right about there then
i'm going to repeat that action by
hitting shift r and holding that down
that will duplicate it all the way up to
the very top
and there we go so now we are ready to
start animating the pages actually
rotating with the book itself now you
might be wondering why we don't just
select the page and then parent that to
the empty and the reason for that is it
just doesn't work that way since i want
some of the pages to actually remain on
the ground as the other pages are moving
up if we parent it to the empty all of
the pages are going to move at the exact
same time and it's not going to look
that good so that's why we're going to
be animating them ourselves without
parenting them to the empties so what
i'll do is i will select all the pages
on the right side all of these just like
this and then on frame 1 i'm going to
hit i and add in a location rotation
keyframe
then we're going to skip to frame 15
we're going to rotate all of these just
like this rotate them 90 degrees and
then holding control i'm going to place
them right at this point here if for
some reason you have a little bit of a
gap in between where they're located
what you can do is select both of the
middle empties right here since i have
an even number i'm going to select two
of them hit shift s and go cursor to
select it then i will select all of the
pages up top
deselect both of these empties we don't
want to select those
then i'll press shift s and go selection
to cursor but keep the offset and that
will make sure that the origins are in
the exact same position
then i'll hit i and add in another
location rotation keyframe
skip to frame 30 we're going to do the
exact same thing rotate the origins by
90 degrees and then place them right
here
but you can see they're still offset a
little bit so what i'll do is i will
select both of the middle empties shift
s
cursor to selected then i will select
all the pages shift s selection to
cursor but keep the offset and then
we'll add in the last location keyframe
now if we restart our animation and play
it here is the result
so now the question is how do we get all
the pages to move separately so they're
not moving at the exact same time this
is actually very easy with this add-on
called commotion if you watch my puzzle
tutorial you'll know exactly how this
works it allows you to offset all the
animation very very easily with one
click of a button so to get this add-on
click the link in the description
download it and install it to install an
add-on go over to user preferences
underneath the add-ons just click
install and then make sure you add that
in by typing in commotion in the search
bar and then making sure it's checked
right there so once you have it
installed let's go over to the second
collection with all of the pages and
then let's select them all
i'm going to select the top page last
this one right here so make sure it's
the active object then i'm going to
press shift s and go cursor to active so
my cursor is placed right at the top
then you can press n and go over to the
commotion tab down at the bottom right
here this offset right here controls how
many frames the animation is actually
offset and then you can click on offset
animation that will do the entire thing
one thing to keep in mind is you don't
want to set one for the offset if you do
this it's going to look a little bit
weird and your animation will look like
it's completely static which does not
look good
so for my animation i'm going to set it
up to a value of two then i'm gonna
click on offset animation
and there you go now if we play our
animation here is the result that we're
getting you can see all of the pages are
moving separately which is looking
really good next up i'm going to select
only half of the pages right about there
and then i'm going to move these
keyframes over to the right so we have a
gap in the middle
so now if we select everything we can
see we have two sets of keyframes i
might drag these a little bit closer
though probably around there now if we
play our animation we can see this is
the effect at this point the pages stop
then they resume right here and it fills
out the rest of the book
that is looking very good and now we
need to fix the animation for the spine
itself so let's go back over to
collection 1 and select the spine
this keyframe right here we need to
duplicate it so it actually remains open
for a period of time so i'm going to
shift d it and move it over to the right
then i'll select both of these keyframes
and drag them over
then all we have to do is line them up
so we can see here it remains open for a
little bit and then at a certain point
the pages start to move
and then right there that is when i want
the book to start closing so what i'll
do is i will select both of these
drag them this way
and then i'll select this keyframe and
drag it a little bit more to the right
so it slows it down
and there we go and finally you're just
going to need to tweak it a little bit
you can see here the page is actually
inside it so what i'll do is i'll just
drag it this way
and just like that we can see it lines
up perfectly
and there you go you can control the
speed of the pages if you want it to go
a little bit faster what you'll have to
do is go back into collection two
i'll restart and select them all
in the offset what you need to do first
is set this back down to zero and then
click on offset animation and that will
reset everything then you can set it up
to let's say if you want it to be slower
you can set it up to four
then what that will do you can see here
the pages are moving a lot slower now
if you want it to be faster first you
have to reset it so set it back down to
zero restart the animation offset it
then if we go with a decimal value like
point five for example the animation
will be really fast
but i'm going to leave it at two i think
that is pretty good so i'm just going to
control z that a couple times just like
that
one thing that i forgot to mention is if
you don't like the height of the pages
what you can do is select all these
empties down here for the hook objects
and then just scale them down along the
z axis this will bring the roundness of
the pages down a lot lower and i think
that looks just a little bit better you
can even go higher if you want them to
be higher like this or lower just
depending on what you want
so there you go that is how you animate
a book opening in blender the next step
is to just add some textures uh one
thing that one thing to keep in mind is
that the texture will actually be a
little bit warped on the piece of paper
because of the hooked modifier so you're
gonna have to scale the uv map just a
little bit to make it look a little bit
better but once you add in some textures
and lighting and render out the
animation you will have a really cool
animation of a book opening
if you created your own animation from
this video make sure to send it to me on
instagram at blendermade easy also
thanks again to skillshare for
sponsoring this video and i will see you
in the next one